Finding Aid for Washtenaw County (Mich.) records, 1824-1946
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Washtenaw County (Mich.) records
1824-1946
Washtenaw County (Mich.)
86193 CB Out. Vol.; Cb/2; Cb Out. Folder
Correspondence files of the county clerk, register of deeds, county treasurer, and other county offices; also township poll lists, political party enrollment books, list of Civil War volunteers, record of county soldiers and sailors during World War I, and miscellaneous welfare records.
14 linear feet in 16 boxes
16 oversize volumes
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were stored at the Washtenaw County Court House and came to the library through the courts records office (donor no. 3148 ) in 1955 and 1956.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The record group is open to research.
Washtenaw County is located in southeastern Michigan.
The record group consists of records of some of the elected officials and departments of the government of Washtenaw County, Michigan. These include the county clerk, register of deeds, and the county treasurer. There are other records relating to elections and to the political party enrollments and to the work of county government in caring for the poor. Of interest are records pertaining to the service of Washtenaw County residents serving in the Civil War and in World War I.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.: Township); Augusta (Mich.: Township); Bridgewater (Mich.: Township); Dexter (Mich.: Township); Elections--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Freedom (Mich.: Township); Hamburg (Mich.: Township); Lima (Mich.: Township); Livingston County (Mich.); Lodi (Mich.: Township); Lyndon (Mich.: Township); Manchester (Mich.: Township); Northfield (Mich.: Township); Pittsfield (Mich.: Township); Public welfare--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Salem (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); Saline (Mich.: Township); Scio (Mich.: Township); Sharon (Washtenaw County, Mich.); Superior (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); Sylvan (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Webster (Mich.); World War, 1914-1918.; Almshouses--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Public welfare--Michigan--Washtenaw County.
- Correspondence
  - County Clerk (Frederick A. Howlett)
    - A-Z, 1887-1890; 22 folders (Box 1)
      (1-1 to 1-22)
  - County Clerk (Arthur Brown)
    - A-Z, 1890-1893; 22 folders (Box 1)
      (1-23 to 1-44)
  - County Clerk (William Dansingburg)
    - A-Z, 1895-1896; 20 folders (Box 1)
      (1-45 to 1-64)
  - County Clerk (Edwin H. Smith)
    - A-Z, 1917-1918; 19 folders (Box 1)
      (1-65 to 1-83)
  - Register of Deeds (Michael Seery)
    - 1889 (Box 2)
      (2-1)
  - Register of Deeds (Andrew T. Hughes)
    - 1893 (Box 2)
      (2-2)
  - Register of Deeds (Carlyle P. McKinstry)
    - A-Z, 1895-1896; 18 folders (Box 2)
      (2-3 to 2-20)
  - Register of Deeds (Clifford R. Huston)
    - A-Z, 1901-1904; 24 folders (Box 2)
      (2-21 to 2-44)
  - County Treasurer (Frederick H. Belser)
    - A-Z, 1886-1888; 12 folders (Box 2)
      (2-45 to 2-56)
  - County Treasurer (Gustave Brehm)
    - A-Z, 1888-1892; 10 folders (Box 3)
      (3-1 to 3-10)
  - County Treasurer (Paul G. Sukey)
    - A-Z, 1892-1894; 10 folders (Box 3)
      (3-11 to 3-20)
  - County Board of Supervisors
    - 1841-1898, undated (Box 3)
      (3-21)
  - Notification of creation of Weinsberg Post Office, 1890 (Box 3)
    (3-22)
  - Compilation of service records for W.W.I veterans, 1919-1921 (Box 3)
    (3-23)
  - Court Stenographer of the Twenty-Second Circuit Court, 1927 (Box 3)
    (3-24)
- County Clerk's Office
  - Coroner inquests, 1843-1910; 39 folders (Box 3)
    (some gaps in dating)
    (3-25 to 3-63)
  - Lists of bank stockholders, 1867-1941; 55 folders (Box 4)
    (4-1 to 4-55)
  - Reports of Inspectors of Jails, 1861-1916; 4 folders (Box 4)
    (4-56 to 4-59)
  - Specifications for new jail, 1885 (Box 4)
    (4-60)
  - Jail boarding reports, 1882-1916 (Box 4)
    (4-61)
  - Miscellaneous sheriff's reports, 1907-1930 (Box 4)
    (4-62)
  - Tavern permits, 1836 (Box 4)
    (4-63)
  - Petitions for road and alley construction, 1827; 1852; 1860 (Box 4)
    (4-64)
  - Miscellaneous business, 1841-1907 (Box 4)
    (4-65)
- Register of Deeds
  - Mortgages A-L, 1830-1940 (Box 5)
    (wrapped in small brown envelopes; in chronological order)
  - Mortgages M-Z, 1830-1940 (Box 6)
  - Writs of Attachment A-Z, 1840-1900 (Box 7)
  - Land patents, 1824-1837; 7 folders (Box 8)
    (8-1 to 8-7)
  - Certificates of probate of wills, 1857-1923; 11 folders (Box 8)
    (8-8 to 8-18)
  - Reports of commissioners and decree of confirmation in partition, 1849-1926; 3 folders (Box 8)
    (8-19 to 8-21)
  - Appointment of guardians for estates of incompetents or spendthrifts, 1846-1890 (Box 8)
    (8-22)
  - Letters of special administration for estates, 1871-1912 (Box 8)
    (8-23)
  - Probate disposition of estates of minors, 1871; 1936 (Box 8)
    (8-24)
  - Probate exemplification of estate records, 1880-1945 (Box 8)
    (8-25)
  - Probate orders determining estate heirs, 1891-1913 (Box 8)
    (8-26)
  - Probate decrees assigning estate residues, 1876-1943; 11 folders (Box 8)
    (8-27 to 8-37)
  - Grants of power of attorney, 1839-1945; 6 folders (Box 8)
    (8-38 to 8-43)
  - Cautions, 1838-1879 (Box 8)
    (8-44)
  - Certificates of property appraisals, 1841-1842 (Box 8)
    (8-45)
  - Leases of various school districts, 1838-1876 (Box 8)
    (8-46)
  - Miscellaneous leases, 1832-1927 (Box 8)
    (8-47)
  - Oil leases, 1927-1936 (Box 8)
    (8-48)
  - Discharge of liens, 1912-1939 (Box 8)
    (8-49)
  - Mortgage tax affidavits, 1911-1913; 1940-1941; 4 folders (Box 8)
    (8-50 to 8-53)
  - Writs of repossession, 1929-1940 (Box 8)
    (8-54)
  - Chattel mortgages, 1937-1943 (Box 8)
    (8-55)
  - Washtenaw County resident book of unpaid mortgages, 1879-1891 (Volume 10)
  - Land transfers, 1890-1892 (Volume 11)
  - Mortgage tax affidavits, August 1911-April 1916 (Volume 12)
  - Miscellaneous contracts, sales and property transfers, 1838-1946; 5 folders (Box 9)
    (9-1 to 9-5)
  - Sworn affidavits, 1866-1942; 3 folders (Box 9)
    (9-6 to 9-8)
  - Church articles of association and bylaws
    - Congregational Foundation at the University of Michigan, 1897 (Box 9)
      (9-9)
    - Evangelical Lutheran Bethel Congregation, Freedom Township, 1899 (Box 9)
      (9-10)
    - First Congregational Church of Dexter, 1901 (Box 9)
      (9-11)
    - Various, 1903-1912; 2 folders (Box 9)
      (9-12 to 9-13)
  - Death certificates, 1914-1940 (Box 9)
    (9-14)
  - Certification of Edward Cash as register of deeds, 1835 (Box 9)
    (9-15)
  - List of Washtenaw County Justices of the Peace, 1836-1850 (Box 9)
  - List of Washtenaw County Justices of the Peace and Notary Publics, 1863-1877 (Box 9)
- Election Records
  - Poll lists, 1837-1844; 21 folders (Box 9)
    (arranged alphabetically by township)
    (microfilm copy available in part)
    (see also oversize folder Cb)
  - Election returns (fragmentary), 1835-1858; 3 folders (Box 9)
  - Political Party Enrollment Books with corrections and additions, 1912-1915 (Box 14)
    (arranged alphabetically by name of township)
    - Ann Arbor Township-Dexter (Box 14)
    - Freedom-Sylvan (Box 15)
    - Webster-Ypsilanti (Box 16)
- Military and veterans materials
  - Military census of Superior Township, 1861 (Box 10)
  - List of Washtenaw County volunteers, Civil War, 1861-1862 (Box 10)
  - Record of Washtenaw County Soldiers and Sailors, World War I
    - A-Haz, 2 volumes (Box 10)
    - He-Sy, 3 volumes (Box 11)
    - Ta-Z (Box 12)
  - Enemy aliens registered in Washtenaw County, World War I (Box 12)
- Welfare Records
  - Superintendent of the Poor record book, 1848-January 1870 (Box 12)
  - Record of Board of Poor Commissioners, 1888-1939 (Box 12)
  - Inmates of county infirmary, 1878-1937 (Volume 1)
  - Register of Washtenaw County Poorhouse, 1884-1886 (Volume 2)
  - Superintendent of the Poor journals
    - October 1886-October 1900 (Volume 3)
    - October 1900-March 1910 (Volume 4)
    - October 1909-September 1914 (Volume 5)
  - Superintendent of the Poor and Insane Asylum accounts, 1876-1882 (Box 12)
  - Report of families of volunteers requiring relief, 1861-1863 (Box 12)
  - Report of families of volunteers requiring relief, 1863-1865 (Volume 6)
  - Volunteer family relief orders, 1865-January 1867 (Volume 7)
  - Ledger, December 1909-July 1914 (Volume 16)
- County Treasurer's Records
  - Assessment roll of Ann Arbor Township, 1841 (Box 12)
  - Assessment for Salem Township, 1843 (Box 12)
  - Ledger, 1858-1866 (Box 12)
    (include some temporary relief records)
  - Ledger, 1872-1877 (Box 12)
  - Record of taxes paid, 1842-1868 (Box 13)
  - General journal, 1839-October 1853 (Box 13)
  - General journal, October 1854-April 1863 (Box 13)
  - Cash receipts ledger, 1858-1862 (Box 13)
  - Cash receipts ledger, 1863-1872 (Box 13)
  - Unpaid land taxes of Washtenaw County, 1827-1844 (Volume 8)
  - Statement of principal and interest due on sales of primary school lands, Washtenaw County, 1851-1871 (Volume 9)
- Miscellaneous
  - County Fair Records, 1871-1889 (Volume 13)
  - List of Washtenaw County physicians, 1901 (Volume 14)
  - Road ledger, 1913-1916 (Volume 15)